<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://emanuelesilviogentile.co.uk/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://emanuelesilviogentile.co.uk/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-08-26T16:38:30+00:00</updated><id>https://emanuelesilviogentile.co.uk/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Emanuele Silvio Gentile, Dr</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Improving Nocturnal Precipitation and Low-Level Jets over the Great Plains with an Advanced Turbulence Representation</title><link href="https://emanuelesilviogentile.co.uk/blog/2025/great-plains-clubb/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Improving Nocturnal Precipitation and Low-Level Jets over the Great Plains with an Advanced Turbulence Representation"/><published>2025-08-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-08-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://emanuelesilviogentile.co.uk/blog/2025/great-plains-clubb</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://emanuelesilviogentile.co.uk/blog/2025/great-plains-clubb/"><![CDATA[<p><em>This post is based on the paper <a href="https://www.authorea.com/users/745948/articles/1325061-enhancing-great-plains-nocturnal-precipitation-and-low-level-jets-in-am4-with-an-extended-clubb-closure">Enhancing Great Plains Nocturnal Precipitation and Low-Level Jets in AM4 with an Extended CLUBB Closure</a>, a collaboration with <a href="https://uwm.edu/math/people/larson-vincent/">Prof. Vince Larson</a>, <a href="https://www.gfdl.noaa.gov/ming-zhao-homepage/">Dr. Ming Zhao</a>, <a href="https://www.met.psu.edu/directory/colin-zarzycki">Prof. Colin Zarzycki</a>, <a href="https://www.su.se/english/profiles/gsven-1.182452" style="color:#28a745;">Prof. Gunilla Svensson</a>, and <a href="https://www.gfdl.noaa.gov/leo-donner-homepage/">Dr. Leo Donner</a>.</em></p> <h2 id="background">Background</h2> <p>The Great Plains of the United States represent one of the most complex natural laboratories for studying convective meteorology and its interaction with strong wind currents flowing from south to north. In summer, this vast region is characterized by a nocturnal maximum of precipitation, linked to the formation of low-level jets (LLJ): intense currents that develop within the first kilometers of the atmosphere and transport large amounts of moisture from the Gulf of Mexico northward. This transport favors the initiation of thunderstorms even in the absence of strong synoptic forcing, making nocturnal convective events a key element of the regional climate.</p> <p>Despite their importance, faithfully reproducing the nocturnal rainfall peak and the structure of LLJs remains a challenge for numerical models, which often tend to generate an erroneous daytime maximum. This is related to convective parameterizations that are overly sensitive to surface thermal instability produced by daytime heating over the Great Plains. Observational campaigns such as PECAN have highlighted these limitations, pointing to the critical role of turbulent processes in the boundary layer for triggering nocturnal convection.</p> <p>To address these limitations, we extended the CLUBB turbulence scheme in the GFDL-AM4 global climate model by introducing two innovations: a <strong>prognostic treatment of momentum fluxes</strong> and a <strong>multiscale turbulent lengthscale</strong>. This configuration was tested to assess its impact on nocturnal summer precipitation and LLJ structure in the Great Plains, comparing results with satellite and radar observations.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="methods">Methods</h2> <p>To improve the representation of the nighttime precipitation peak over the Great Plains, we used the GFDL-AM4 global climate model, developed at the Geophysical Fluid Dynamics Laboratory (NOAA). AM4 has a horizontal resolution of about 100 km and includes parameterizations for convection, clouds, and boundary-layer turbulence.</p> <p>In this work, the CLUBB turbulence scheme (Cloud Layers Unified By Binormals) was extended to replace the standard AM4 parameterizations, introducing two main innovations:</p> <p>Prognostic momentum flux treatment In traditional models, vertical momentum fluxes (the turbulent exchange of momentum) are handled in a simplified way using a diagnostic momentum flux (AM4-CLUBB_DM configuration in this study), which corresponds to a “diffusive” gradient-based approach. This method cannot reproduce counter-gradient fluxes that emerge in nocturnal Low-Level Jets, where air masses can propagate above the jet core. With the prognostic momentum flux (AM4-CLUBB_PM configuration), the fluxes evolve dynamically, making it possible to capture such effects (Larson et al., 2019).</p> <p>Multiscale turbulent length scale In the traditional version of CLUBB, a single turbulent length scale governs all turbulent processes. In the new scheme, however, different characteristic times and length scales are used for different variables and fluxes (e.g., temperature, humidity, vertical velocity). This makes the parameterization more realistic, as it reflects the fact that turbulent eddies do not all share the same characteristic size—hence a multiscale turbulent length scale (Guo et al., 2021). This approach leads to two additional configurations: AM4-CLUBB_DM_X or AM4-CLUBB_PM_X, depending on whether the diagnostic or prognostic momentum flux is used.</p> <p>To isolate the effects of these modifications, five distinct simulations were carried out: one control run with standard AM4, and four with the extended CLUBB scheme, varying the combination of diagnostic/prognostic approach (AM4-CLUBB_DM and AM4-CLUBB_PM) and single/multiscale turbulent length scale (AM4-CLUBB_DM_X and AM4-CLUBB_PM_X).</p> <p>The evaluation of results relied on:</p> <p>Satellite precipitation data (IMERG, NASA), which provide high-frequency, high-resolution estimates of the diurnal rainfall cycle;</p> <p>Wind profiles from lidar and radar profilers at the ARM Southern Great Plains site (Oklahoma), one of the most comprehensive in the world, allowing direct observation of the formation and intensification of nocturnal low-level jets.</p> <p>The comparison between simulations and observations enabled assessment of both the phase and amplitude of the diurnal precipitation cycle, as well as the vertical structure of the jet and associated moisture transport fields.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="results">Results</h2> <p>The reference simulations with GFDL-AM4 reproduce the model’s well-known bias (Fig. 1): the diurnal cycle of summer precipitation over the Great Plains shows an afternoon maximum instead of a nocturnal one, with an average lead of 6–8 hours compared to IMERG satellite observations. The amplitude of the cycle is also too weak, with values nearly halved relative to observations. This deficit is tightly linked to the model’s difficulty in representing Low-Level Jets (LLJs) and the associated nighttime moisture transport from the Gulf of Mexico.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/greatplains_fig1-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/greatplains_fig1-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/greatplains_fig1-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/greatplains_fig1.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="70%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Figure1: Mean characteristics of precipitation and diurnal cycle during boreal summer (JJA) over the Contiguous United States (CONUS). Panels (a–c–e) show respectively: (a) the mean precipitation rate [mm day⁻¹], (c) the amplitude [mm day⁻¹], and (e) the phase [hour of maximum in LST] derived from the satellite product IMERG. Panels (b–d–f) report the corresponding fields from the AM4 control simulation. The phase is defined as the local solar time (LST) of the precipitation peak, while the amplitude corresponds to the magnitude of the first diurnal harmonic. The phase scale is circular (0–24 LST), with warmer colors indicating afternoon maxima and cooler colors indicating nocturnal or early morning maxima.</figcaption> </figure> <p>The implementation of the CLUBB scheme produces the first improvements (Fig. 2a,c,e). Simulations with diagnostic momentum fluxes (AM4-CLUBB_DM) slightly reduce the phase bias, shifting the precipitation maximum toward the evening hours. A more substantial improvement emerges with the prognostic treatment of momentum fluxes (AM4-CLUBB_PM): here, the precipitation peak occurs around 03 UTC on average, much closer to the observed 01–02 UTC. The amplitude of the diurnal cycle also increases, leading to an overall 40% improvement compared to the standard model version.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/greatplains_fig2-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/greatplains_fig2-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/greatplains_fig2-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/greatplains_fig2.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="70%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Same as Fig. 1 but for the AM4 configuration with CLUBB employing the diagnostic momentum flux (a–c–e) and for the AM4 configuration combining prognostic momentum flux with the multiscale turbulent length scale.</figcaption> </figure> <p>Introducing the multiscale turbulent length scale in combination with prognostic momentum fluxes (AM4-CLUBB_PM_X) yields further benefits (Fig. 2b,d,f). Mean nocturnal precipitation over the central Great Plains approaches satellite-derived values, with the bias reduced to less than –1 mm/day (compared with –3 mm/day in the control simulation). The hourly distribution also exhibits a clear nocturnal maximum and a more pronounced afternoon minimum, indicating a more realistic coupling between the stable PBL and nocturnal convection.</p> <p>Additional analyses with AM4 coupled to the extended CLUBB turbulence scheme reveal how parameterization choices crucially affect the representation of the nocturnal LLJ over the Great Plains (Fig. 3). In the nocturnal vertical profiles, both the diagnostic and prognostic momentum flux versions with a single turbulent length scale (AM4-CLUBB_DM and AM4-CLUBB_PM) confine turbulent activity to the lowest ~200 m, with rapid decay of fluxes and variances above this level. In contrast, the multiscale formulation sustains water vapor and liquid potential temperature fluxes well beyond 2000 m (AM4-CLUBB_DM_X and AM4-CLUBB_PM_X), accompanied by enhanced vertical velocity skewness and stronger nocturnal convection.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/greatplains_fig3-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/greatplains_fig3-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/greatplains_fig3-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/greatplains_fig3.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="70%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Figure 3. Vertical profiles of selected CLUBB higher-order moments such as moisture flux (a), vertical velocity variance (b), and skewness (c). The baseline CLUBB configuration in AM4 (AM4-CLUBB_DM) is shown in orange; the version that directly prognoses the momentum flux (AM4-CLUBB_PM) in pink; and the versions that add the multiscale turbulent length scale to the diagnostic (AM4-CLUBB_DM_X) or prognostic (AM4-CLUBB_PM_X) momentum flux are shown in green and dark blue, respectively.</figcaption> </figure> <p>Regarding the LLJ structure, all configurations capture the main features of the observed summertime circulation. However, adopting prognostic momentum fluxes strengthens the jet by ~2 m/s compared to the diagnostic configuration, particularly near the Rocky Mountains. By contrast, the multiscale turbulent length scale tends to weaken the jet, with winds up to 2.5 m/s slower in the jet core.</p> <p>Comparison with ARM Southern Great Plains observations (Fig.4) indicates that the diagnostic momentum flux version reproduces jet intensity reasonably well, whereas the prognostic version introduces stronger anisotropy and places the LLJ core too high. Using the multiscale turbulent length scale together with prognostic fluxes partly mitigates these discrepancies, reducing vertical shear and bringing the jet depth closer to that typical of the planetary boundary layer.</p> <p>Finally, analysis of the momentum flux budgets highlights that the multiscale formulation substantially enhances buoyancy-driven turbulence production, promoting more frequent counter-gradient fluxes and pointing to a stronger role of deep, non-local eddies in nighttime mixing around the LLJ core.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/greatplains_fig4-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/greatplains_fig4-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/greatplains_fig4-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/greatplains_fig4.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="70%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Figure 4. Vertical profiles of the meridional wind over the Great Plains in Oklahoma. The colors follow the scheme in Fig. 3, with the addition of the original AM4 configuration without CLUBB (blue) and the ARM observations (black).</figcaption> </figure> <hr/> <h2 id="conclusions">Conclusions</h2> <p>This study demonstrates that a more realistic representation of subgrid scalar and momentum turbulent transport can yield substantial improvements in simulating key regional processes. The combined use of prognostic momentum flux and multiscale turbulent lengthscale in CLUBB significantly reduced the nocturnal precipitation phase bias over the Great Plains while also improving LLJ intensity and Gulf moisture transport.</p> <p>Importantly, these advances were achieved without ad hoc parameter tuning, but solely by introducing turbulence physics more faithful to the underlying Navier–Stokes equations. This reinforces the idea that the evolution of climate models does not only rely on higher resolution but also on a more accurate representation of unresolved processes in the model core.</p> <p>However, with ~100 km grid spacing, a global model like AM4 cannot reproduce mesoscale convective systems that drive much of the nocturnal rainfall maximum. A natural next step is to transfer these innovations to km-scale global models, where the “gray zone” between parameterized turbulence and resolved convection opens new challenges. In parallel, integrating artificial intelligence and machine learning approaches may further refine subgrid turbulence representation, with benefits extending beyond the Great Plains to the prediction of global extreme events.</p> <hr/>]]></content><author><name>Emanuele Silvio Gentile</name></author><category term="blog"/><category term="climate"/><category term="turbulence"/><category term="CLUBB"/><category term="AM4"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[English version of my contribution to AISAM newsletter based on my JAMES paper which shows how extending the higher-order scheme CLUBB improves the nocturnal precipitation peak on the Great Plains along with the associated Low-Level Jet wind structure.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Poleward Intensification of Midlatitude Extreme Winds Under Warmer Climate</title><link href="https://emanuelesilviogentile.co.uk/blog/2024/gfdl-highlight/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Poleward Intensification of Midlatitude Extreme Winds Under Warmer Climate"/><published>2024-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://emanuelesilviogentile.co.uk/blog/2024/gfdl-highlight</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://emanuelesilviogentile.co.uk/blog/2024/gfdl-highlight/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>npj Climate and Atmospheric Science</strong><br/> <strong>Authors:</strong> Emanuele Silvio Gentile, <a href="https://www.gfdl.noaa.gov/ming-zhao-homepage/">Ming Zhao</a>, <a href="https://research.reading.ac.uk/meteorology/people/kevin-hodges/">Kevin Hodges</a> <strong>DOI:</strong> <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41612-023-00540-x">10.1038/s41612-023-00540-x</a></p> <hr/> <p>Focusing on climate-induced changes in winds, I investigated how midlatitude cyclones impact the global distribution of extreme wind speed events, defined as those exceeding the climatological 99th percentile, across both hemispheres in a warmer climate. The study uses the state-of-the-art GFDL atmospheric climate model AM4, with a grid spacing of approximately 50 kilometers, covering the period from 1949 to 2019. The authors analyzed scenarios representing present-day climate conditions and an idealized future projection characterized by global warming conditions with a uniform sea surface temperature (SST) increase of 2K. The findings of the investigation yield several key insights: there is an increase in near-surface extreme wind speeds of up to 3%/K towards the polar regions, while there is a corresponding decrease in the midlatitudes. There is a clear trend of midlatitude cyclones associated with extreme wind speeds migrating towards higher latitudes. One particularly notable finding is the interaction between midlatitude cyclones and extreme wind events. Despite an overall reduction in the number of midlatitude cyclones by approximately 4% in the warmer climate, there is a significant increase in the proportion of cyclone-associated extreme wind speeds by 10%. This highlights the changing nature of extreme wind occurrences in a warmer climate.</p> <p>Additionally, the study identifies specific regions, such as Northwestern Europe, the British Isles, and the West Coast of North America, as areas of heightened concern due to the amplified impacts of cyclone-associated extreme winds in a warmer climate, which in turn has socio-economic consequences.</p> <p>While the research findings provide critical insights into the complex interplay between midlatitude cyclones, extreme wind events, and climate change, the authors emphasize the importance of understanding the dynamics of midlatitude cyclones amidst human-induced climate change. This understanding is crucial for developing effective climate adaptation strategies and mitigating associated risks. The study also highlights the importance of extreme wind events in vulnerable areas but it acknowledges limitations, including the simplified assumption of uniform SST warming and the overlooked decline in sea-ice cover, which necessitate further examination of the complexities of cyclonic activity in a warming future.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/poleward-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/poleward-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/poleward-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/poleward.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="70%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">This map illustrates the percentage change in extreme wind speeds, defined as daily maximum wind speeds (DMWS) exceeding the climatological 99th percentile, for each degree of sea surface temperature (SST) warming according to AM4 climate model simulations. The analysis reveals how the median of the 99th-100th percentile daily maximum 10-meter wind speeds, corresponding to the 99.5th percentile (v99.5), shifts per degree of SST warming across both the (a) Northern Hemisphere (NH) and (b) Southern Hemisphere (SH) in an idealized warmer climate scenario</figcaption> </figure>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog"/><category term="climate"/><category term="extreme wind"/><category term="extratropical cyclones"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Repost of the npj Climate and Atmospheric Science research highlight in the GFDL/NOAA winter bulletin]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Machine Learning: complement or replacement of Numerical Weather Prediction?</title><link href="https://emanuelesilviogentile.co.uk/blog/2021/social-metwork-gentile/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Machine Learning: complement or replacement of Numerical Weather Prediction?"/><published>2021-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://emanuelesilviogentile.co.uk/blog/2021/social-metwork-gentile</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://emanuelesilviogentile.co.uk/blog/2021/social-metwork-gentile/"><![CDATA[<p>You can read my full post on <a href="https://socialmetwork.blog/author/emanuelesilviogentile/">The Social Metwork</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Personal opinion post on the future of machine learning for weather prediction.]]></summary></entry></feed>