<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://emanuelesilviogentile.co.uk/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://emanuelesilviogentile.co.uk/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-12-23T12:07:14+00:00</updated><id>https://emanuelesilviogentile.co.uk/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Emanuele Silvio Gentile, Dr</title><subtitle>&quot;Research, papers, personal blogs, teaching, and what’s next at the intersection of climate, turbulence, and AI. Keen to collaborate, have a look and say hi.&quot; </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Challenges and Opportunities for AI and Kilometer-Scale Climate Modelling of Precipitation</title><link href="https://emanuelesilviogentile.co.uk/blog/2025/ai-km-precip/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Challenges and Opportunities for AI and Kilometer-Scale Climate Modelling of Precipitation"/><published>2025-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://emanuelesilviogentile.co.uk/blog/2025/ai-km-precip</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://emanuelesilviogentile.co.uk/blog/2025/ai-km-precip/"><![CDATA[<p>Challenges and Opportunities for AI and Kilometer-Scale Climate Modelling of Precipitation<br/> Author: Emanuele Silvio Gentile, Dr<br/> The preprint on which this post is based is available <a href="https://essopenarchive.org/doi/full/10.22541/essoar.176538317.73098714">here</a>.</p> <p>One of the enduring challenges in weather and climate modelling is not predicting <em>how much</em> it rains, but <em>when</em>. The diurnal cycle of precipitation, the systematic daily rhythm through which rainfall builds, peaks, and decays, emerges from a tight coupling between radiation, surface fluxes, boundary-layer growth, convection, cloud microphysics, and mesoscale organisation. Because it integrates processes across scales, the diurnal cycle has long served as a stringent test of physical realism in atmospheric models.</p> <p>Historically, even state-of-the-art weather and global climate models have struggled with this diagnostic. Rainfall over land tends to begin too early in the day, peak prematurely in the afternoon, and decay too rapidly overnight. Nocturnal precipitation, a defining feature of many continental and monsoon regions, is often weak or entirely absent. Yet these same models can perform well on bulk metrics such as monthly means or spatial correlations, creating a misleading impression of skill.</p> <p>In a recent preprint, we revisit the diurnal precipitation cycle as a <strong>process-level benchmark</strong>, using it to compare a state-of-the-art AI weather prediction system (GraphCast), a widely used reanalysis product (ERA5), satellite observations (IMERG), and a global convection-permitting simulation at 5-km resolution. The central question is simple: <em>what does the diurnal cycle reveal that headline skill scores do not?</em></p> <hr/> <h3 id="models-and-datasets">Models and datasets</h3> <p>The comparison spans four distinct modelling paradigms. IMERG provides the observational reference, offering high-temporal-resolution satellite estimates of precipitation. ERA5 represents the best current synthesis of observations and model physics and serves as the training backbone for many machine-learning systems. GraphCast, a graph neural network trained on ERA5, exemplifies the new generation of data-driven weather models capable of producing skilful forecasts at unprecedented speed. Finally, a global 5-km Unified Model simulation offers a view of what changes when deep convection is largely explicitly resolved rather than parameterised.</p> <p>All datasets are analysed consistently, focusing on boreal summer (JJAS) and decomposing precipitation into its mean state, the amplitude of the diurnal harmonic, and the phase (local solar time of peak rainfall).</p> <hr/> <h3 id="diagnosing-the-diurnal-cycle">Diagnosing the diurnal cycle</h3> <p>To move beyond mean fields, we decompose precipitation into its leading diurnal harmonic. Two quantities are particularly informative: the <strong>amplitude</strong>, which measures how strongly rainfall is modulated by the daily cycle, and the <strong>phase</strong>, which indicates the local time at which precipitation peaks.</p> <p>These diagnostics allow us to distinguish between models that merely reproduce the right amount of rain and those that capture the physical processes governing its evolution through the day.</p> <h3 id="a-stable-observational-reference">A stable observational reference</h3> <p>Before comparing models, it is essential to establish whether interannual variability could confound the analysis. Using IMERG observations for boreal summer 2021 and 2023, we find that the <strong>global diurnal precipitation cycle is remarkably stable</strong>.</p> <p>Mean precipitation patterns differ only modestly between the two seasons, with 2023 slightly wetter over parts of the tropical oceans. More importantly, the <strong>structure of the diurnal cycle itself — amplitude and timing — is nearly unchanged</strong>. Strong diurnal amplitudes persist over continental interiors and coastal regions, while precipitation peaks consistently occur in the late afternoon to early evening over land and during the early morning over tropical oceans.</p> <p>This stability confirms that the seasonal mismatch between datasets (IMERG and the UM 5-km simulation in 2021 versus ERA5 and GraphCast in 2023) does not compromise the intercomparison. The diurnal cycle provides a robust, physically interpretable benchmark against which different modelling approaches can be evaluated.</p> <div style="text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/fig_1-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/fig_1-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/fig_1-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/fig_1.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="70%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">GLobal Mean precipitation characteristics and diurnal cycle during boreal summer JJA. Panels (a-c-e) show the (a) mean precipitation rate [mm~day$^{-1}$], (c) amplitude [mm~day$^{-1}$], and (e) phase [hour of maximum in LST] derived from the IMERG observational product for the 2021 JJA. Panels (b-d-f) display the corresponding fields from the 2023 JJA. Phase is defined as the LST peak precipitation in the diurnal harmonic, and amplitude corresponds to the magnitude of the first harmonic. The phase scale is circular (0-24 LST), with warmer colors indicating afternoon peak times, while cooler colors indicating night or early morning peak times.</figcaption> </figure> </div> <hr/> <h3 id="mean-precipitation-agreement-without-physical-insight">Mean precipitation: agreement without physical insight</h3> <p>At first glance, all three models — ERA5, GraphCast, and the 5-km Unified Model — reproduce the broad spatial structure of observed mean precipitation. Tropical rainfall maxima along the ITCZ and over the Maritime Continent are evident, as are secondary maxima over regions such as the Great Plains, central Africa, and the Southern Ocean.</p> <p>However, this apparent agreement is deceptive. Mean precipitation integrates over the full diurnal cycle and therefore masks compensating errors.</p> <div style="text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/fig_2_v2-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/fig_2_v2-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/fig_2_v2-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/fig_2_v2.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="50%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Mean precipitation rate as in Fig. 1a,b but for ERA5 (a), GraphCast (b), and the UM 5-km model (c). Note that ERA5 and GraphCast refer to JJA~2021 while the UM 5-km simulation to JJA~2023.</figcaption> </figure> </div> <p>ERA5 overestimates rainfall along the eastern Pacific ITCZ and underestimates it across large parts of the Maritime Continent. GraphCast broadly mirrors the ERA5 pattern but produces noticeably smaller regions of intense rainfall, with underestimations of up to ~5 mm day⁻¹ across parts of the Atlantic and Pacific ITCZ.</p> <p>The experimental 5-km Unified Model reproduces the location and magnitude of tropical precipitation maxima more faithfully, but at the cost of a substantial wet bias in the midlatitudes, particularly over the Southern Ocean and parts of Europe and North America.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="diurnal-amplitude-where-models-begin-to-diverge">Diurnal amplitude: where models begin to diverge</h3> <p>Much larger discrepancies emerge when considering the <strong>amplitude of the diurnal precipitation cycle</strong>.</p> <div style="text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/fig3_v2-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/fig3_v2-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/fig3_v2-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/fig3_v2.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="50%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Diurnal amplitude of precipitation as in Fig. 1c,d but for ERA5 (a), GraphCast (b), and the UM 5-km model (c).</figcaption> </figure> </div> <p>ERA5 substantially underestimates this amplitude. Over the Great Plains, diurnal modulation is weak and spatially fragmented, while over the Maritime Continent and coastal Mexico the areas of strong diurnal variability are far smaller than observed.</p> <p>GraphCast not only inherits these deficiencies but often <strong>amplifies them</strong>, producing systematically weaker amplitudes across primary and secondary convective regions.</p> <p>By contrast, the 5-km Unified Model closely matches observed diurnal amplitudes across most regions, with only minor regional biases.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="phase-timing-errors-dominate-over-land">Phase: timing errors dominate over land</h3> <p>The <strong>timing of peak precipitation</strong> provides the clearest separation between modelling approaches.</p> <div style="text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/fig4_v2-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/fig4_v2-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/fig4_v2-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/fig4_v2.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="50%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Phase of precipitation as in Fig. 1e,f but for ERA5 (a), GraphCast (b), and the UM 5-km experimental model (c).</figcaption> </figure> </div> <p>ERA5 exhibits a pronounced bias toward premature rainfall over land, with precipitation peaking around midday or early afternoon rather than late afternoon or evening.</p> <p>GraphCast further degrades this behaviour, concentrating rainfall unrealistically near local noon and producing very weak nocturnal precipitation. Over oceans, GraphCast also peaks too early, failing to reproduce the observed early-morning maximum.</p> <p>The 5-km Unified Model shows clear improvements in nocturnal precipitation and captures several regional phase characteristics, although early afternoon peaks persist over some land regions.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="landocean-contrasts-organisation-matters">Land–ocean contrasts: organisation matters</h3> <p>Domain-averaged diurnal cycles over land and ocean further clarify these behaviours.</p> <div style="text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/fig_4_new-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/fig_4_new-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/fig_4_new-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/fig_4_new.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="60%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Domain averaged hourly precipitation (units: mm day$^{-1}$) wihtout projection to first harmonic over (a) global land (b) tropical ocean (c) Africa (d) Asia, (e) Europe, (f) Central US for IMERG JJA2021 (blue lines), IMERG JJA 2023 (orange lines), ERA5 JJA 2023 (green lines), GraphCast JJA 2023 (red lines), UM 5-km JJA 2021 (purple lines).</figcaption> </figure> </div> <p>ERA5 broadly reproduces the tropical-ocean diurnal cycle but peaks too early over land and underestimates nighttime rainfall. The 5-km Unified Model substantially reduces these nocturnal deficits, while GraphCast exhibits the largest phase bias, peaking roughly four hours too early and failing to capture organised nocturnal convection.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="discussion-and-conclusions">Discussion and conclusions</h2> <p>This analysis provides a process-based perspective on the strengths and limitations of AI-based weather prediction when evaluated against a physically demanding benchmark: the diurnal cycle of precipitation.</p> <p>GraphCast successfully reproduces the large-scale spatial distribution of mean rainfall, reflecting the information content of its ERA5 training data. However, it systematically underestimates diurnal amplitude and substantially degrades the timing of precipitation, particularly over land. In several respects, GraphCast amplifies known ERA5 biases, producing a compressed diurnal cycle dominated by premature, surface-forced convection and weak nocturnal rainfall.</p> <p>In contrast, the experimental global 5-km Unified Model demonstrates clear benefits of explicitly resolving deep convection and mesoscale organisation. Improvements in diurnal amplitude and nocturnal precipitation bring the simulation closer to observations, particularly over regions dominated by organised convection. Nonetheless, persistent wet biases and early afternoon peaks highlight that even kilometre-scale models remain sensitive to boundary-layer physics, microphysics, and scale-aware convective closures.</p> <p>Overall, neither AI-based nor physics-based approaches fully resolve long-standing deficiencies in the diurnal precipitation cycle. The diurnal cycle therefore remains a <strong>crucial and physically interpretable benchmark</strong> for evaluating future weather and climate models. Progress will likely require <strong>hybrid AI–physics frameworks</strong> that combine the physical realism of kilometre-scale simulations with the computational efficiency of AI, and that explicitly target sub-daily variability during model development and training.</p> <h3 id="what-this-implies-for-ai-weather-prediction">What this implies for AI weather prediction</h3> <p>GraphCast represents a major advance in weather forecasting. Its computational efficiency and forecast skill make it operationally transformative. However, the diurnal cycle exposes a fundamental limitation of purely data-driven approaches trained on reanalysis products: they cannot outperform the physical realism of their training data at the process level.</p> <p>This is not a failure of AI, but a reflection of how learning systems work. AI models excel at reproducing patterns that are present in the data. They do not, on their own, recover physical processes that are systematically missing.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="why-kilometer-scale-physics-still-matters">Why kilometer-scale physics still matters</h3> <p>The global 5-km simulation demonstrates that explicitly resolving deep convection alters not just the magnitude of precipitation, but its temporal character. Nocturnal systems emerge more naturally, amplitudes increase, and phase errors are reduced. While kilometer-scale modelling does not eliminate all biases, it provides a physically grounded reference against which both parameterised models and AI systems can be evaluated.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="toward-hybrid-futures">Toward hybrid futures</h3> <p>The broader implication is not a choice between physics and AI, but their integration. Convection-permitting simulations offer a pathway to improve both parameterisations and machine-learning models, whether through training data, physically informed loss functions, or hybrid architectures that embed constraints directly into learning systems.</p> <p>The diurnal precipitation cycle should play a central role in this effort. As a diagnostic, it reveals whether models merely look right in aggregate or behave realistically in time.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="final-reflections">Final reflections</h3> <p>Sub-daily precipitation is not a niche detail. It is a window into how models represent the atmosphere. By focusing on <em>when</em> rain falls, rather than only <em>how much</em>, we gain sharper insight into the strengths and limitations of both AI-based and physics-based weather prediction systems.</p> <p>📌 <strong>Preprint available here:</strong><br/> The preprint is available <a href="https://essopenarchive.org/doi/full/10.22541/essoar.176538317.73098714">here</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog"/><category term="climate"/><category term="precipitation"/><category term="diurnal cycle"/><category term="AI"/><category term="GraphCast"/><category term="km-scale modelling"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[What sub-daily precipitation reveals about GraphCast, reanalysis, and kilometer-scale climate physics]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Kilometer-Scale Climate Intelligence for a Regenerative Urban Future</title><link href="https://emanuelesilviogentile.co.uk/blog/2025/bioplanning_climate/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Kilometer-Scale Climate Intelligence for a Regenerative Urban Future"/><published>2025-08-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-08-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://emanuelesilviogentile.co.uk/blog/2025/bioplanning_climate</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://emanuelesilviogentile.co.uk/blog/2025/bioplanning_climate/"><![CDATA[<p>Kilometer-Scale Climate Intelligence for a Regenerative Urban Future<br/> Author: Emanuele Silvio Gentile, Dr</p> <p>One of the paradoxes of climate-informed design is that while global climate models have become increasingly robust, their coarse scale often limits their usefulness for local decision-making [1-2]. The models that underpin international assessments typically resolve the atmosphere at 50 to 200 kilometres, yet the interventions that determine ecological and social resilience, restoring a wetland, safeguarding a biodiversity corridor, designing an urban cooling strategy, unfold at scales of tens or hundreds of metres [3]. Bridging this disconnect between abstract global projections and the lived experience of climate on the ground is one of the central challenges of bioplanning.</p> <p>Recent breakthroughs are beginning to close this gap. A new generation of high-resolution datasets now makes it possible to model temperature, precipitation, solar radiation and humidity at resolutions finer than one kilometre. CHELSA-BIOCLIM+ [4], for instance, provides global, downscaled climate surfaces tailored for ecological applications, while new land-cover projections aligned with IPCC scenarios [5] allow planners to anticipate how landscapes may evolve under different socioeconomic pathways. Figure 1 illustrates this leap in detail: where older maps smoothed climate over entire regions, kilometre-scale data reveals the fine structure of valleys, ridges, and coastlines that shape ecological function.</p> <div style="text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/km-scale_mountains-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/km-scale_mountains-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/km-scale_mountains-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/km-scale_mountains.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="70%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Figure 1. Global climate model representation of California elevations (left) compared to km-scale precision climate information (right). Adapted from [6].</figcaption> </figure> </div> <p>For the first time, planners can identify micro-refugia, assess species’ habitat suitability, or design conservation corridors with a resolution that matches ecological realities. Equally transformative is the arrival of artificial intelligence in climate science. NASA and IBM recently introduced the first open-source foundation model for weather and climate, which allows kilometre-scale downscaling, extreme-event forecasting, and flexible seasonal scenario analysis. By fine-tuning the model with local data, planners and communities gain access to forecasting capacity that until recently required scarcely available supercomputing resources. At the same time, Google DeepMind’s AlphaEarth Foundations integrate satellite observations with generative AI to anticipate floods, wildfires, and heatwaves across scales [7]. Operational tools like Flood Hub, FireSat and the Solar API (the latter for solar and energy systems installations) are already assisting countless countries in monitoring disaster risk and optimising urban infrastructure. Figure 2 highlights the high-realism of the output of this workflow: raw climate and Earth-observation data feed through foundation models and AI algorithms to produce microclimate maps, disaster risk forecasts, and design-ready intelligence.</p> <div style="text-align: center;"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/alpha_earth-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/alpha_earth-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/alpha_earth-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/alpha_earth.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="70%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Figure 2. Example of how Google DeepMind’s AlphaEarth can visualize with unprecedented realism the fine details of our world. This snapshot illustrates agricultural land parcels in Ecuador, resolved clearly despite the presence of cloud cover that would normally obstruct conventional satellite imagery. Such AI-enabled reconstruction demonstrates how foundation models can transform raw Earth observations into decision-ready intelligence. Taken from [7].</figcaption> </figure> </div> <p>These innovations are not simply technical feats. They mark the emergence of a new planning paradigm. With kilometre-scale data and AI-enabled analysis, it becomes possible to simulate how an urban expansion might alter local rainfall patterns through to 2100, or how a wetland restoration will affect water availability under a plausible 2°C warmer world. Hydrological changes, soil moisture dynamics, species distributions, even the spatial variability of urban heat, all can now be assessed with a fidelity that aligns with the scales at which communities and ecosystems operate. For bioplanning, this is the difference between designing against an abstract backdrop and designing in tune with the actual climatic grain of place.</p> <p>The implications are profound. Conservationists can safeguard climate refugia and connectivity corridors, municipalities can test the resilience of green infrastructure under future extremes; architects and engineers can integrate climate intelligence into the earliest stages of design. And crucially, these assessments are transparent and reproducible. Projects such as Supernature Lab’s regenerative frameworks can now be monitored and evaluated with science-based intelligence that fosters trust across biodiversity, carbon, and infrastructure sectors.</p> <p>The convergence of high-resolution climate data, backed by increasingly high-fidelity physical understanding and representation, along with the rapidly emerging AI innovations in climate modelling is therefore more than a technical advance. It represents a paradigm shift for sustainable urbanism: one in which design and policy can finally align with the climatic realities of place, informed by the precision and speed of next-generation data. The ecological cities of tomorrow will not be imagined in spite of the climate system, but in dialogue with it.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="references">References</h3> <ol> <li>Schneider, T., Leung, L. R., and Wills, R. C. J.: Opinion: Optimizing climate models with process knowledge, resolution, and artificial intelligence, <em>Atmos. Chem. Phys.</em>, 24, 7041–7062, https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-24-7041-2024, 2024.</li> <li>Slingo, J., Bates, P., Bauer, P. et al. Ambitious partnership needed for reliable climate prediction. <em>Nat. Clim. Chang.</em> 12, 499–503 (2022). https://doi.org/10.1038/s41558-022-01384-8</li> <li>Smith, A. P., Yung, L., Snitker, A. J., Bocinsky, R. K., Metcalf, E. C., &amp; Jencso, K. (2021). Scalar mismatches and underlying factors for underutilization of climate information: Perspectives from farmers and ranchers. <em>Frontiers in Climate</em>, 3, Article 663071. https://doi.org/10.3389/fclim.2021.663071</li> <li>Karger, D.N., Conrad, O., Böhner, J., Kawohl, T., Kreft, H., Soria-Auza, R.W., Zimmermann, N.E., Linder, P., Kessler, M. (2017). Climatologies at high resolution for the Earth land surface areas. <em>Scientific Data</em>, 4, 170122. https://doi.org/10.1038/sdata.2017.122</li> <li>Hengl, T., de Jesus, J. M., Heuvelink, G. B. M., Gonzalez, M. R., Kilibarda, M., Blagotić, A., Shangguan, W., Wright, M. N., Geng, X., Bauer-Marschallinger, B., Guevara, M. A., Vargas, R., MacMillan, R. A., Batjes, N. H., Leenaars, J. G. B., Ribeiro, E., Wheeler, I., Mantel, S., &amp; Kempen, B. (2021). SoilGrids250m: Global gridded soil information based on machine learning. <em>Earth System Science Data</em>, 13(2), 415–434. https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-13-415-2021</li> <li>https://today.ucsd.edu/story/new_high_resolution_climate_projections_aim_to_better_represent_extreme_eve?utm_source=chatgpt.com</li> <li>https://deepmind.google/discover/blog/alphaearth-foundations-helps-map-our-planet-in-unprecedented-detail/</li> </ol>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog"/><category term="climate"/><category term="bioplanning"/><category term="urban design"/><category term="high-resolution modelling"/><category term="AI"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Climate-informed design and bioplanning at kilometre scale]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Improving Nocturnal Precipitation and Low-Level Jets over the Great Plains with an Advanced Turbulence Representation</title><link href="https://emanuelesilviogentile.co.uk/blog/2025/great-plains-clubb/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Improving Nocturnal Precipitation and Low-Level Jets over the Great Plains with an Advanced Turbulence Representation"/><published>2025-08-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-08-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://emanuelesilviogentile.co.uk/blog/2025/great-plains-clubb</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://emanuelesilviogentile.co.uk/blog/2025/great-plains-clubb/"><![CDATA[<p><em>This post is based on the paper <a href="https://www.authorea.com/users/745948/articles/1325061-enhancing-great-plains-nocturnal-precipitation-and-low-level-jets-in-am4-with-an-extended-clubb-closure">Enhancing Great Plains Nocturnal Precipitation and Low-Level Jets in AM4 with an Extended CLUBB Closure</a>, a collaboration with <a href="https://uwm.edu/math/people/larson-vincent/">Prof. Vince Larson</a>, <a href="https://www.gfdl.noaa.gov/ming-zhao-homepage/">Dr. Ming Zhao</a>, <a href="https://www.met.psu.edu/directory/colin-zarzycki">Prof. Colin Zarzycki</a>, <a href="https://www.su.se/english/profiles/gsven-1.182452" style="color:#28a745;">Prof. Gunilla Svensson</a>, and <a href="https://www.gfdl.noaa.gov/leo-donner-homepage/">Dr. Leo Donner</a>.</em></p> <h2 id="background">Background</h2> <p>The Great Plains of the United States represent one of the most complex natural laboratories for studying convective meteorology and its interaction with strong wind currents flowing from south to north. In summer, this vast region is characterized by a nocturnal maximum of precipitation, linked to the formation of low-level jets (LLJ): intense currents that develop within the first kilometers of the atmosphere and transport large amounts of moisture from the Gulf of Mexico northward. This transport favors the initiation of thunderstorms even in the absence of strong synoptic forcing, making nocturnal convective events a key element of the regional climate.</p> <p>Despite their importance, faithfully reproducing the nocturnal rainfall peak and the structure of LLJs remains a challenge for numerical models, which often tend to generate an erroneous daytime maximum. This is related to convective parameterizations that are overly sensitive to surface thermal instability produced by daytime heating over the Great Plains. Observational campaigns such as PECAN have highlighted these limitations, pointing to the critical role of turbulent processes in the boundary layer for triggering nocturnal convection.</p> <p>To address these limitations, we extended the CLUBB turbulence scheme in the GFDL-AM4 global climate model by introducing two innovations: a <strong>prognostic treatment of momentum fluxes</strong> and a <strong>multiscale turbulent lengthscale</strong>. This configuration was tested to assess its impact on nocturnal summer precipitation and LLJ structure in the Great Plains, comparing results with satellite and radar observations.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="methods">Methods</h2> <p>To improve the representation of the nighttime precipitation peak over the Great Plains, we used the GFDL-AM4 global climate model, developed at the Geophysical Fluid Dynamics Laboratory (NOAA). AM4 has a horizontal resolution of about 100 km and includes parameterizations for convection, clouds, and boundary-layer turbulence.</p> <p>In this work, the CLUBB turbulence scheme (Cloud Layers Unified By Binormals) was extended to replace the standard AM4 parameterizations, introducing two main innovations:</p> <p>Prognostic momentum flux treatment In traditional models, vertical momentum fluxes (the turbulent exchange of momentum) are handled in a simplified way using a diagnostic momentum flux (AM4-CLUBB_DM configuration in this study), which corresponds to a “diffusive” gradient-based approach. This method cannot reproduce counter-gradient fluxes that emerge in nocturnal Low-Level Jets, where air masses can propagate above the jet core. With the prognostic momentum flux (AM4-CLUBB_PM configuration), the fluxes evolve dynamically, making it possible to capture such effects (Larson et al., 2019).</p> <p>Multiscale turbulent length scale In the traditional version of CLUBB, a single turbulent length scale governs all turbulent processes. In the new scheme, however, different characteristic times and length scales are used for different variables and fluxes (e.g., temperature, humidity, vertical velocity). This makes the parameterization more realistic, as it reflects the fact that turbulent eddies do not all share the same characteristic size—hence a multiscale turbulent length scale (Guo et al., 2021). This approach leads to two additional configurations: AM4-CLUBB_DM_X or AM4-CLUBB_PM_X, depending on whether the diagnostic or prognostic momentum flux is used.</p> <p>To isolate the effects of these modifications, five distinct simulations were carried out: one control run with standard AM4, and four with the extended CLUBB scheme, varying the combination of diagnostic/prognostic approach (AM4-CLUBB_DM and AM4-CLUBB_PM) and single/multiscale turbulent length scale (AM4-CLUBB_DM_X and AM4-CLUBB_PM_X).</p> <p>The evaluation of results relied on:</p> <p>Satellite precipitation data (IMERG, NASA), which provide high-frequency, high-resolution estimates of the diurnal rainfall cycle;</p> <p>Wind profiles from lidar and radar profilers at the ARM Southern Great Plains site (Oklahoma), one of the most comprehensive in the world, allowing direct observation of the formation and intensification of nocturnal low-level jets.</p> <p>The comparison between simulations and observations enabled assessment of both the phase and amplitude of the diurnal precipitation cycle, as well as the vertical structure of the jet and associated moisture transport fields.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="results">Results</h2> <p>The reference simulations with GFDL-AM4 reproduce the model’s well-known bias (Fig. 1): the diurnal cycle of summer precipitation over the Great Plains shows an afternoon maximum instead of a nocturnal one, with an average lead of 6–8 hours compared to IMERG satellite observations. The amplitude of the cycle is also too weak, with values nearly halved relative to observations. This deficit is tightly linked to the model’s difficulty in representing Low-Level Jets (LLJs) and the associated nighttime moisture transport from the Gulf of Mexico.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/greatplains_fig1-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/greatplains_fig1-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/greatplains_fig1-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/greatplains_fig1.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="70%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Figure1: Mean characteristics of precipitation and diurnal cycle during boreal summer (JJA) over the Contiguous United States (CONUS). Panels (a–c–e) show respectively: (a) the mean precipitation rate [mm day⁻¹], (c) the amplitude [mm day⁻¹], and (e) the phase [hour of maximum in LST] derived from the satellite product IMERG. Panels (b–d–f) report the corresponding fields from the AM4 control simulation. The phase is defined as the local solar time (LST) of the precipitation peak, while the amplitude corresponds to the magnitude of the first diurnal harmonic. The phase scale is circular (0–24 LST), with warmer colors indicating afternoon maxima and cooler colors indicating nocturnal or early morning maxima.</figcaption> </figure> <p>The implementation of the CLUBB scheme produces the first improvements (Fig. 2a,c,e). Simulations with diagnostic momentum fluxes (AM4-CLUBB_DM) slightly reduce the phase bias, shifting the precipitation maximum toward the evening hours. A more substantial improvement emerges with the prognostic treatment of momentum fluxes (AM4-CLUBB_PM): here, the precipitation peak occurs around 03 UTC on average, much closer to the observed 01–02 UTC. The amplitude of the diurnal cycle also increases, leading to an overall 40% improvement compared to the standard model version.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/greatplains_fig2-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/greatplains_fig2-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/greatplains_fig2-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/greatplains_fig2.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="70%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Same as Fig. 1 but for the AM4 configuration with CLUBB employing the diagnostic momentum flux (a–c–e) and for the AM4 configuration combining prognostic momentum flux with the multiscale turbulent length scale.</figcaption> </figure> <p>Introducing the multiscale turbulent length scale in combination with prognostic momentum fluxes (AM4-CLUBB_PM_X) yields further benefits (Fig. 2b,d,f). Mean nocturnal precipitation over the central Great Plains approaches satellite-derived values, with the bias reduced to less than –1 mm/day (compared with –3 mm/day in the control simulation). The hourly distribution also exhibits a clear nocturnal maximum and a more pronounced afternoon minimum, indicating a more realistic coupling between the stable PBL and nocturnal convection.</p> <p>Additional analyses with AM4 coupled to the extended CLUBB turbulence scheme reveal how parameterization choices crucially affect the representation of the nocturnal LLJ over the Great Plains (Fig. 3). In the nocturnal vertical profiles, both the diagnostic and prognostic momentum flux versions with a single turbulent length scale (AM4-CLUBB_DM and AM4-CLUBB_PM) confine turbulent activity to the lowest ~200 m, with rapid decay of fluxes and variances above this level. In contrast, the multiscale formulation sustains water vapor and liquid potential temperature fluxes well beyond 2000 m (AM4-CLUBB_DM_X and AM4-CLUBB_PM_X), accompanied by enhanced vertical velocity skewness and stronger nocturnal convection.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/greatplains_fig3-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/greatplains_fig3-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/greatplains_fig3-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/greatplains_fig3.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="70%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Figure 3. Vertical profiles of selected CLUBB higher-order moments such as moisture flux (a), vertical velocity variance (b), and skewness (c). The baseline CLUBB configuration in AM4 (AM4-CLUBB_DM) is shown in orange; the version that directly prognoses the momentum flux (AM4-CLUBB_PM) in pink; and the versions that add the multiscale turbulent length scale to the diagnostic (AM4-CLUBB_DM_X) or prognostic (AM4-CLUBB_PM_X) momentum flux are shown in green and dark blue, respectively.</figcaption> </figure> <p>Regarding the LLJ structure, all configurations capture the main features of the observed summertime circulation. However, adopting prognostic momentum fluxes strengthens the jet by ~2 m/s compared to the diagnostic configuration, particularly near the Rocky Mountains. By contrast, the multiscale turbulent length scale tends to weaken the jet, with winds up to 2.5 m/s slower in the jet core.</p> <p>Comparison with ARM Southern Great Plains observations (Fig.4) indicates that the diagnostic momentum flux version reproduces jet intensity reasonably well, whereas the prognostic version introduces stronger anisotropy and places the LLJ core too high. Using the multiscale turbulent length scale together with prognostic fluxes partly mitigates these discrepancies, reducing vertical shear and bringing the jet depth closer to that typical of the planetary boundary layer.</p> <p>Finally, analysis of the momentum flux budgets highlights that the multiscale formulation substantially enhances buoyancy-driven turbulence production, promoting more frequent counter-gradient fluxes and pointing to a stronger role of deep, non-local eddies in nighttime mixing around the LLJ core.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/greatplains_fig4-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/greatplains_fig4-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/greatplains_fig4-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/greatplains_fig4.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="70%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Figure 4. Vertical profiles of the meridional wind over the Great Plains in Oklahoma. The colors follow the scheme in Fig. 3, with the addition of the original AM4 configuration without CLUBB (blue) and the ARM observations (black).</figcaption> </figure> <hr/> <h2 id="conclusions">Conclusions</h2> <p>This study demonstrates that a more realistic representation of subgrid scalar and momentum turbulent transport can yield substantial improvements in simulating key regional processes. The combined use of prognostic momentum flux and multiscale turbulent lengthscale in CLUBB significantly reduced the nocturnal precipitation phase bias over the Great Plains while also improving LLJ intensity and Gulf moisture transport.</p> <p>Importantly, these advances were achieved without ad hoc parameter tuning, but solely by introducing turbulence physics more faithful to the underlying Navier–Stokes equations. This reinforces the idea that the evolution of climate models does not only rely on higher resolution but also on a more accurate representation of unresolved processes in the model core.</p> <p>However, with ~100 km grid spacing, a global model like AM4 cannot reproduce mesoscale convective systems that drive much of the nocturnal rainfall maximum. A natural next step is to transfer these innovations to km-scale global models, where the “gray zone” between parameterized turbulence and resolved convection opens new challenges. In parallel, integrating artificial intelligence and machine learning approaches may further refine subgrid turbulence representation, with benefits extending beyond the Great Plains to the prediction of global extreme events.</p> <hr/>]]></content><author><name>Emanuele Silvio Gentile</name></author><category term="blog"/><category term="climate"/><category term="turbulence"/><category term="CLUBB"/><category term="AM4"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[English version of my contribution to AISAM newsletter based on my JAMES paper which shows how extending the higher-order scheme CLUBB improves the nocturnal precipitation peak on the Great Plains along with the associated Low-Level Jet wind structure.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Poleward Intensification of Midlatitude Extreme Winds Under Warmer Climate</title><link href="https://emanuelesilviogentile.co.uk/blog/2024/gfdl-highlight/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Poleward Intensification of Midlatitude Extreme Winds Under Warmer Climate"/><published>2024-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://emanuelesilviogentile.co.uk/blog/2024/gfdl-highlight</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://emanuelesilviogentile.co.uk/blog/2024/gfdl-highlight/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>npj Climate and Atmospheric Science</strong><br/> <strong>Authors:</strong> Emanuele Silvio Gentile, <a href="https://www.gfdl.noaa.gov/ming-zhao-homepage/">Ming Zhao</a>, <a href="https://research.reading.ac.uk/meteorology/people/kevin-hodges/">Kevin Hodges</a> <strong>DOI:</strong> <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41612-023-00540-x">10.1038/s41612-023-00540-x</a></p> <hr/> <p>Focusing on climate-induced changes in winds, I investigated how midlatitude cyclones impact the global distribution of extreme wind speed events, defined as those exceeding the climatological 99th percentile, across both hemispheres in a warmer climate. The study uses the state-of-the-art GFDL atmospheric climate model AM4, with a grid spacing of approximately 50 kilometers, covering the period from 1949 to 2019. The authors analyzed scenarios representing present-day climate conditions and an idealized future projection characterized by global warming conditions with a uniform sea surface temperature (SST) increase of 2K. The findings of the investigation yield several key insights: there is an increase in near-surface extreme wind speeds of up to 3%/K towards the polar regions, while there is a corresponding decrease in the midlatitudes. There is a clear trend of midlatitude cyclones associated with extreme wind speeds migrating towards higher latitudes. One particularly notable finding is the interaction between midlatitude cyclones and extreme wind events. Despite an overall reduction in the number of midlatitude cyclones by approximately 4% in the warmer climate, there is a significant increase in the proportion of cyclone-associated extreme wind speeds by 10%. This highlights the changing nature of extreme wind occurrences in a warmer climate.</p> <p>Additionally, the study identifies specific regions, such as Northwestern Europe, the British Isles, and the West Coast of North America, as areas of heightened concern due to the amplified impacts of cyclone-associated extreme winds in a warmer climate, which in turn has socio-economic consequences.</p> <p>While the research findings provide critical insights into the complex interplay between midlatitude cyclones, extreme wind events, and climate change, the authors emphasize the importance of understanding the dynamics of midlatitude cyclones amidst human-induced climate change. This understanding is crucial for developing effective climate adaptation strategies and mitigating associated risks. The study also highlights the importance of extreme wind events in vulnerable areas but it acknowledges limitations, including the simplified assumption of uniform SST warming and the overlooked decline in sea-ice cover, which necessitate further examination of the complexities of cyclonic activity in a warming future.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/poleward-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/poleward-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/poleward-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/poleward.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="70%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">This map illustrates the percentage change in extreme wind speeds, defined as daily maximum wind speeds (DMWS) exceeding the climatological 99th percentile, for each degree of sea surface temperature (SST) warming according to AM4 climate model simulations. The analysis reveals how the median of the 99th-100th percentile daily maximum 10-meter wind speeds, corresponding to the 99.5th percentile (v99.5), shifts per degree of SST warming across both the (a) Northern Hemisphere (NH) and (b) Southern Hemisphere (SH) in an idealized warmer climate scenario</figcaption> </figure>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog"/><category term="climate"/><category term="extreme wind"/><category term="extratropical cyclones"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Repost of the npj Climate and Atmospheric Science research highlight in the GFDL/NOAA winter bulletin]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Machine Learning: complement or replacement of Numerical Weather Prediction?</title><link href="https://emanuelesilviogentile.co.uk/blog/2021/social-metwork-gentile/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Machine Learning: complement or replacement of Numerical Weather Prediction?"/><published>2021-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://emanuelesilviogentile.co.uk/blog/2021/social-metwork-gentile</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://emanuelesilviogentile.co.uk/blog/2021/social-metwork-gentile/"><![CDATA[<p>You can read my full post on <a href="https://socialmetwork.blog/author/emanuelesilviogentile/">The Social Metwork</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Personal opinion post on the future of machine learning for weather prediction.]]></summary></entry></feed>